this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
[Music]
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program welcome listeners
to another episode on software
engineering radio this episode is
special we have a David Anderson as
guest talking with him about the agile
method Kanban and the interview is done
in cooperation with the German magazine
objects spectrum so I will not ask the
questions but a colleague of mine an
Evoque who's not a member of software
engineer radio will ask the questions
and talk with David about Kanban and we
would like to say thank you to the
objective magazine for sharing this
interview with us and I will hand over
to Anna for this interview have fun
hello David it's nice to have you here
in Germany please introduce yourself and
tell us how did you come to Kanban and
how are you busy with Kanban oh well
thank you for having me Arnie thanks for
inviting me it's nice to be here in
Frankfurt actually my first time here in
the city of Frankfurt I've been many
times to Germany this is the first time
how did I come to Canberra and it's kind
of a big question it's it's been an
evolution over about ten years and total
first working with feature driven
development
Nigel method before we even knew what
agile methods were and learning from
that experience and evolving that a
little by introducing some ideas from
lean and some theories some ideas from
Theory of Constraints and I published
those in my book the agile management
for software engineering book in 2003
and from that I learned a little more I
and I had a challenge a problem that I
was looking at why twice I tried to
introduce feature driven development and
with some success on individual projects
or with teams who reported to me
directly
and with that success I was then asked
to scale the the adoption of feats of
German development across a whole
business unit and both times I tried to
do that at Sprint PCS which is a cell
phone operator in the United States and
then with Motorola which is a cell phone
manufacturer in the United States on
both times trying to scale it to
multiple teams it met with huge
resistance and it didn't
institutionalize and I started to think
about why why wouldn't people just see
the obvious benefits and do the right
thing
why were they resisting and why were we
struggling and I came to the conclusion
that when you come along with if you
like a prescriptive definition of a new
process and tell people they have to
adopt it and they have to change their
perhaps the job description the way of
working the techniques they're using
they resist so it may be better to try a
technique that would allow evolution
rather than revolution and through a you
know a series of events I came to
realize that implementing a Kanban
system may be a way of provoking that
evolution rather than than using your
prescriptive method and asking for a
revolutionary change and that turned out
to be correct
so during at the time between sort of
2004 and 2007 I was trying that out with
a couple of teams at different places
until I had some confidence that it was
working right and started talking about
it publicly and other people lessened
and they tried it and here we are
another two years later and there's
really lots of teams all over the world
trying this now trying this approach of
using Kanban to drive evolution Airi
change rather than more of an agile
revolution if you like
okay could you please explain Kanban in
two sentences okay I'm not sure about
two sentences but very briefly Kanban is
a very simple idea that you choose to
limit the quantity of work in progress
that you visualize that work in progress
using some mechanism such as a
whiteboard with sticky notes on it and
that you only start new work when you
finish some existing work so there's a
signaling mechanism that that shows we
finish something we can now pool a new
item to start so that's it it's a
visualization mechanism with a work in
progress limit and a signaling mechanism
to pull new work when something is
completed right now everyone is talking
about scrum worldwide there are over
61,000 certified scrum masters almost
every company has already developed
scrum or intends to introduce Grum why
then do we still need Kanban so I think
this is a good observation that scrum
really has been remarkably successful
and you can't discount that you know if
there's three or four hundred thousand
people who have the project management
professional certification around the
world for scrum to get to sixty one
thousand certified scrum masters in in
just a few years is a huge achievement
and there's no doubt in my mind that
that scrum is owned as a recipe that
works in particular circumstances in
fact I think its core to the scrum
philosophy that scrum is a recipe that
works and what you should do is change
your circumstances to fit with it so it
has some nice rules that really help it
be successful we'll have fixed length
sprints in the original you know days
810 years ago those were four weeks so
you'd agree that at the beginning of the
four weeks we would make an agreement on
the scope the backlog for the Sprint and
we do four weeks of
mark and a customer wasn't allowed to
interfere with those which is a
fantastic way of eliminating
randomization and very a variability the
customers not allowed to change anything
for four weeks that's a really good
thing and we'd we'd have mechanism like
a daily stand-up meeting where the team
would get together and talk about the
work and that would create a good team
spirit and perhaps some peer pressure to
keep everyone accountable the team would
sign up for the sprint commitment the
backlog at the beginning and they'd all
work together to get that finished at
the end and then we demo something
working to the customer and have a
retrospective all these things are
really good
the challenge with it is doing things to
that that rhythm you know for weeks is
not right maybe two weeks is right but
are we forcing things to work like that
you know I don't buy the idea that scrum
works for every situation in fact I'm
sure that we've met you and I have met
people today who came along to the class
that we've been holding specifically
because they had situations that scrum
wasn't very applicable for like IT
operations and systems maintenance the
concept that they would batch things up
into a backlog of two weeks or four
weeks of work is really quite alien for
them so I think it's very understandable
why scrum is a huge success I don't buy
the idea that it works everywhere and I
think that in the situations where it's
applicable it's wildly successful
because it's very constraining and the
the rules are very you know precisely
chosen to prevent interference and let
people get on with the work and allow
them to self-organize inside the box the
you know the sprint box the team box the
the rules are well chosen and are
designed for success
under I personally feel a limited set of
circumstances and those rules are quite
simple they're easy to understand if you
can learn it in one and a half or two
days of training and it can't be so
difficult so it's no surprise to me it's
been hugely successful I'm sure it's a
big improvement on some other ways of
doing project management but it's also
clear to me that it doesn't solve every
problem and just trying to bash people
harder and harder by saying you're not
doing it right
isn't the right answer and I I feel that
those value and being open minded in
thinking about other approaches a scrum
and Kanban competing methods or both are
complementing one another so I don't see
them as competing methods because Kanban
is not a development methodology or a
project management methodology and while
I've seen the scrum community recently
try and redefine what scrum is only that
there are if you like competing
redefinitions of it if you read the
early books it's essentially a project
management methodology
there's no engineering content in there
in fact a lot of scrum people will say
you need extreme programming along with
scrum so that you have engineering and
you have project management Kanban is
neither of these things it's not an
engineering method or a project
management method it's a change
management method it's a way of
provoking change and provoking change
that leads to a lean organization a
continuously improving culture a case in
culture it's a way of provoking
incremental evolutionary changes in an
organization rather than trying to to
revolutionize with a new way of working
you don't do Kanban on it's a win so
people will come to me all they'll post
something on the internet that says we
have a new team and we haven't chosen
the method
ecology yet should we do Kanban or scrum
and to me that that doesn't compute as a
question because you have to do Kanban
on top of something else so the very
first team we did Kanban with was a
personal software process team software
process team so a PSP TSP team working
at an outsourced vendor in India for
Microsoft and we added Kanban on top of
TSP PSP we didn't change TSP PSP we left
that unchanged we put Kanban on top of
it and we travelled the productivity of
the team and reduced the cycle time by
90 percent
the next team we did it with was a good
old fashioned waterfall method team
doing a methodology that came out of the
1970s if you like and since then we've
seen lots of teams adopt Kanban in
different situations and there have been
teams that have added Kanban to scrum
the problem is that when you add Kanban
to scrum very quickly begins to change
scrum the team start asking questions
like why are we doing - we cater Asians
and and Kanban helps them decouple
things like the the input the
prioritization and planning from the
output the releasing mechanism and and
also the cycle time and scrum these
three things are connected they're
they're coupled so if you have a
two-week sprint you're planning every
two weeks your cycle time is two weeks
and you're releasing every two weeks and
for some organizations that's not the
best choice so when they start doing
Kanban very soon they start to challenge
what's the rate cadence and the the
decouple the input from the cycle time
from the output well if you're no longer
doing Sprint's that have a fixed length
of two weeks or four weeks
is it still scrum and that's one of the
challenges because the scrum community
has thrown out this
standard this gets referred to as the
Nokia test for evaluating how well
you're doing scrum and if you can't pass
the test you're somehow not doing scrum
as the implication so that to me creates
the sannyasa in the scrum community you
know the idea originally I believed was
that you dead scrum and it encouraged
you to start improving well if you start
improving you should be changing a scrum
team that's good at scrum a year later
should be doing something that's unique
and different and wouldn't necessarily
look like scrum anymore and that I see
the scrum community struggling with that
dichotomy of how can you be continuously
improving if you have to prove that
you're doing scrum according to the test
so so we've seen teams apply Kanban on
top of scrum and in fact my friend Cory
laddus wrote a whole book on that topic
it's called scrum ban and it's how to
apply Kanban to scrum and it talks about
how scrum teams would evolve and
ultimately they evolve to doing
something that doesn't look like scrum
anymore the truth at scrums more people
centric why Kanban is more about the
business value whoa I don't know if
that's true
let's talk about business value later I
hear this criticism that usually comes
from from extreme programming or scrum
people in the agile community people who
generally haven't tried Kanban and
they'll say things like Kanban doesn't
respect people and actually I find that
it's really completely there of a us the
the policies involved in implementing a
Kanban system have a huge amount of
respect for people they're incredibly
empowering the empower the team to
self-organize but they make the
mechanism very
what's it so that managers understand
how self-organizing works and they also
understand how the rules of
self-organization align to the risk
management policies for the organization
so managers trust the team more they
trust the self-organizing the agile
community uses self-organizing a lot you
know the bandy the term around and it
scales managers and big companies to
death you know and I see some leaders in
the scrum community saying things like
managers are irrelevant or managers are
not needed if you have a really good
scrum team you don't need a manager well
if you're a manager that's very
threatening it makes you fearful and why
would you encourage adoption of scrum
eff if you believe what you're being
told that you're no longer necessary so
I think that that's a very bad message
the agile community does itself a
disservice by sending the message that
manage what managers are bad and
management is unnecessary what they
should really be saying is that that
there is such a thing as bad management
and that that bad management can be
turned into good management and good
managers empower people and empowerment
can be implemented through policies that
allow people to self organize and make
their own choices and Kanban is very
good at helping with that also the work
in progress limit in Kanban is a
tremendously powerful way of protecting
the team from abuse if you have an
agreement on the quantity of work in
progress and you've balanced that
quantity correctly then no one should be
working overtime the agile manifesto
principle of achieving a sustainable
piece of work is very easily achieved if
you agree a work in progress limit so
Kanban for me is a really fabulous and
straightforward and simple way of of
achieving that sustained
Pease and helping team members acquire a
proper balance between work and the rest
of the life and what could be more
respectful of people than helping them
achieve that balance similar to scrum
Kanban does not specify certain
development practices are there any
practices you prefer with an ikemen
system so I think there are some
practices that are required for canva
and to be successful particularly if
you're doing canva and in software
development you need to have a
capability to release software you know
if it's an internet type application or
an IT systems you need to be able to
release it to production if it's a
product company perhaps you know there's
more to do with you know manufacturing
CDs and printing them and shipping them
off and having them stacked on shelves
and games companies for example they
still do physical manufacturing but
there needs to be this release
capability and if you backup from that
then you need a core configuration
management capability you need to be
able to identify in track requirements
you need to be able to version control
software and manage branches and the it
you know in that system you need to be
able to merge branches appropriately and
select items for release and make sure
that the right things get released and
things which are not finished yet don't
get released in the wild by accident so
configuration management is a core
capability that is required to enable
Kanban to work and it doesn't need to be
super sophisticated I think most agile
teams most teams doing extreme
programming have that capability already
they know how to track user stories they
know how to version control they know
how to do branches they know how to do
continuous integration they know how to
package up
executable software for release so so
while it's a necessary capability and
behavior it's not uncommon I have seen
one or two people say you know I had
this team they were really lousy at
scrum so we switched them to Kanban and
they were still lousy and when you
questioned why they were lousy it was
well they couldn't release and why
couldn't they release well they were
uncapable incapable of building the
software why couldn't they build it
because they didn't have good
configuration management so that's the I
think the core capability that's
required to meet Kanban mark what about
test-driven development I think that's
fine
you know do it if you want to and if you
don't do it
Kanban isn't going to mind the
engineering practices are really
agnostic to the concept of limiting work
in progress and only starting something
new when you finish something that
you're working on if a team's not doing
test-driven development and you came
along and said I want you to do
test-driven development they might see
why and you could have a whole
discussion with them about why it may be
a good idea but you you know what you're
trying to do is persuade people
it's an emotional level of discussion
and what Kanban tends to do is allow
problems to be visualized so let's say
for example that the defect rate in code
is a problem and it's it's limiting the
quantity that's getting completed it's
lengthening the cycle times it's making
delivery dates unreliable
an improvement in quality is required
and when the team can see that and they
can see the effect of the defects they
might choose to start writing unit tests
fast and that would improve some of the
initial quality and then perhaps things
get into system level testing and fail
and have to go back and that may cause a
discussion about wouldn't it be good if
we define the tests upfront so that we
you know we had thought about that
problem earlier in the lifecycle and the
cord was designed so it would pass the
test so it passes first time and
everything flows better so Kanban will
expose the problems and allow the team
to have a discussion about how to fix it
and if the improvement required was
introducing TDD then that will become
their conclusion the team will realize
it for themselves and will implement it
on their own they're not being forced
so they own the change and it's much
more likely to institutionalize and the
adoption will be faster and better if
they conclude that they should do it
rather than have somebody push it on
them in which context as a child in
Kanban so there's been this question
about agile in canva and particularly
because the first two case studies that
were published the first one was based
on a PSP TSP team and as there's a lot
of debate about TSP PSP and Barry Boehm
and Richard tunnels book on balancing
agility and discipline they really
defined PSP TSP as a non ideal method
however the software engineering
Institute continued to dispute that and
and would argue that PSP as an agile
method but I think that that the
consensus opinion is PSP is not agile
and the second case study we had was a
team doing waterfall plus Kanban
so that clearly wasn't agile either
so why would Kanban be agile
particularly when it has all these
strict policies about work in progress
limits and so on
well I really try and look at the core
ideas behind the agile manifesto and I
boiled those down to agile is about
making progress with imperfect
information rather than trying to seek
perfect information to rate that beg
perfect requirement document and to do
lots of analysis agile says you know
what let's spend a little bit of time
figuring stuff out and then get started
like start writing the code and if we
learn more later on we'll refactor
because that's cheaper so that agile
makes an assumption that there's a
better economic outcome from moving
forward with imperfect information and
that cycle times and costs will be law
from refactoring rather than trying to
be perfect up front so if you look at
that concept and canva and that there's
no conflict
Kanban would allow you to move things
forward with imperfect information in
fact the the sort of agnostic a Kanban
would be agnostic to whether you had
perfect information or not whatever your
policy is for pooling is acceptable so
if you don't if you only have 80% of the
information you need and you're allowed
to pull say from analysis to development
that would be okay so that the second
idea behind the agile manifesto is the
concept of a high trust culture in the
workplace that people are empowered that
we trust them that we show individuals a
lot of respect and Kanban really
enforces that in fact it codifies it and
as a mechanism as a as a catalyst for
growing a lean
organization a Kaizen culture Kanban
really builds a lot of trust
Kanban requires you to meet regular
releases and that those releases should
be high-quality and to collaborate
across the team across the organization
collaborate with upstream people like
marketing people so lots of
collaboration is high trust work in
progress limits have make you know our
mechanism when something becomes blocked
things get stuck and when when work in
progress is stark and other people
become idle because the limit prevents
them from starting something the
idleness tends to cause a swarming
behavior the the G you know I've got
nothing to do right now how can I help
you get this other thing unstuck and
Henrich neiberg from sweden put together
a really interesting cartoon which if
you you know if someone listening to
this google's for it you know can ban
cartoon they'll see a little story about
how the team swarms on problems and
collaborates together so Kanban actually
encourages collaboration and improves
the level of trust in the organization
and it's somewhat counterintuitive
because intuitively we think that high
trust cultures have very few rules and
that's not necessarily true they have
lots of rules that define the boundaries
and then sayed the boundary people get
to self-organize and spontaneously
affiliate and swarm on problems and fix
them and the the third concept in the
manifesto is the idea that cycle time is
really important and that work in
progress is at best a depreciating asset
that the market is changing you know so
if we have an idea for a product a
service a feature in a piece
software that idea only has so much of a
life and at some point in the future
it's it's not worth anything or it's
worth a lot less it's commoditized
perhaps so if we have an idea for a
really cool differentiating feature in
our product and it takes us six months
to develop and get it in the market but
three months after we had the idea our
competitor launches that feature then
the value is greatly depreciated so the
idea is that you should get those
features developed quickly as fast as
you can and put them in the market to
maximize the value so so a best ideas
for software are depreciating assets
requirements user stories features
whatever you want to call them so it's
better to think about them as
liabilities and keep them moving really
quickly then to think about them as
assets and hold them so when you think
about something as a liability it
encourages you to have a smaller
quantity to have really small batches
and when the agile community understood
that they started making iteration sizes
smaller
so four weeks wasn't as good as two
weeks and one week was even better than
two weeks so smaller batch sizes smaller
cycle time treating work-in-progress is
thought was a liability
well Kanban encourages that by allowing
you to set a wet limit and then
encouraging you to decrease that limit
over time and to focus on cycle time as
a metric so I find that Kanban meets all
the criteria it allows you to move
forward with imperfect information it
encourages a high trust culture and it
encourages a focus on cycle time and to
treat working progress is low it's a
liability rather than an asset so it's
really highly compatible with agile
values in former days you're engaged in
future driven development as Kanban an
approach to develop FTD features without
overhead so yeah so I had this you know
wonderful benefit in my career in my
life of being involved in future driven
development and the team there and just
a marvelous group of people who came
together for that project
I think Kanban for me evolved out of a
lot of learnings in future driven
development it's not like I tried to
improve FDD with Kanban but if I had
never done FTD and I hadn't learned from
that and evolved some of the thinking
from lean like cumulative flow diagrams
and thinking about the full problem and
from that thinking about Theory of
Constraints and understanding
bottlenecks and how to relieve them if I
hadn't gone through that series of
learnings I wouldn't have ended up at
Kanban but I don't see you know a direct
relationship I understand an evolution
and my thinking over a period of years
but I you know I held some of the I saw
some you know commentary on the internet
about can ban was optimizing future
driven development and I I don't
directly connect them it can ban the
appropriate approach if an organization
wants to become a guy or is it more of
an advanced approach so I again I've
seen a lot of talk on the internet you
know blog posts people tweeting on
Twitter people expressing opinions at
conferences and it generally takes the
the theme of Kanban is a more advanced
approach and you ought to get good at
scrum before you try Kanban my
observation is people saying that are
all people who one have never tried
Kanban and two generally have a vested
interest and you becoming good at scrum
first the reason that I think this is
clearly not true is the first team that
dead Kanban was a PSP TSP team the
second team was a waterfall team and
most of the public
case studies that we have from two
conferences that we've held now and and
some publications and say developer comm
well there's a case study from Robert
Bosch another online publication called
gamasutra has a case study from a games
company with a specific focus on games
production
none of these examples had the team
become good at scrum fast before they
got good at Kanban so no one who's had
success with canva and we'd say that
we'd say you should be good at scrum
first and then there's this question of
is can ban a more advanced technique
well it is evident from experience that
some teams that do can buy and mature
very rapidly if they were being assessed
on the capability maturity model
integration scale we clearly have
several teams that have gone from
relatively amateur in chaotic to really
quite high maturity quantitatively
managed CMMI level four sort of behavior
and really very short periods of time
nine months 12 months 15 months
accelerated achievement of high maturity
but they started at very wal maturity
and really the only prerequisite in my
opinion as a capability at configuration
management as I stated earlier in the
interview and if you look on the CMMI
model configuration management is a
level 2 behavior and it's one of the
first capabilities that's generally
recommended for you know for any team
that's in chaos if they can't track and
manage the configurations that they
won't get very far so I think there's
plenty of evidence that teams have
benefited from canva and
even if they're very immature they've
benefited from canva and even if they're
not agile but the benefits have tended
to go further and go go follow faster
than we've seen with other agile methods
and the reason that I'm still doing
Kanban and I'm advocating it is because
I've seen teams achieve things that I
hadn't managed other ways I hadn't
managed earlier in my career and I see
that it's a you know a huge positive for
years and years it was marked by the
agile communities we need time boxes to
realistically be able to measure the
progress of the project but you call for
finishing the tyranny of time boxes why
so there's a you know a number of ideas
and behind that first of all the agile
manifesto does not state that that time
box declarations are required the
wording actually says that we should
release software every two to eight
weeks
with a preference for the smaller time
it's the release cadence that's
important and not the time box so I
think the authors of the manifesto got
it right but thinking back to 2001 or
earlier this decade if you said to
someone the goal is to release software
every two weeks the only tool they had
at hand for making that work was a time
boxed iteration you know a one-week
two-week a four week box of time and as
I had mentioned earlier that time box
couples together three really distinct
things the first one is how often can we
meet with the business to prioritize and
plan what we should be working on the
second thing is how long does it take to
analyze design code and test a user
story or a feature or a use case or you
know functional requirement or whatever
they're called in your organization
and the third thing is how often can we
do a release and it turns out that these
things have have different elements
involved how often can we meet with the
business is a factor of the coordination
cost of having that meeting more often
would be better than less often it would
be better to have more prioritization
information more often it should allow a
more optimum outcome and how long does
it take to code a user story is entirely
unrelated to how often can we meet with
the the business owners or the marketing
department so why would you couple those
things together why force a two-week
planning meeting with a two-week cycle
time for coding up user stories you know
these things should be allowed to be
decoupled that's a good principle and
software engineering why don't we apply
it process engineering and the same
would go on the other end of the scale
with how often can we do a release so we
had a really fascinating example the
last time we did the Kanban class in
Hamburg where one of the attendees was
from a steel manufacturing company here
in Germany and after he'd been through
the class he had figured out that they
could meet with the business once a week
to do prioritization that was a
perfectly reasonable thing to do and the
cycle time for most of the work which
was relatively involved would take about
six weeks to do analysis design
development and testing but they were
deploying the software to control a hot
rolling steel mill and the cost of
shutting that thing down to upgrade the
software is phenomenal you know the the
the the value of the steel that's going
through the mail every hour is a lot of
money so they're only willing to do that
once every six months because that
there's a tremendous cost of shutting it
down and then spending it back up
and it's very risky so they want to have
plenty of time to test everything and
make sure that they're really
comfortable that the code the deploying
is defect-free
because they can't afford to try and
spin up the steel male and have a crash
so there was an example of a one-week
cycle time for prioritization a sec
sorry one-week cadence for
prioritization a 6-week cycle time for
development and a six-month cadence for
deployment it's quite clear from that
example that something any agile method
would say a two-week Ithorian length is
not a good fit for that problem space so
by decoupling these things and allowing
them to move freely we're we're freeing
the organization from the tyranny of the
time box a lot of people say that
retrospectives are the heart of agile
approaches what about retrospective and
Kanban so it's very clear that you can't
learn anything unless you take the time
to stop and reflect and with Kanban I've
encouraged teams to create more of an
organizational level activity to stop
and reflect and I call those operations
reviews and they're not new I didn't
invent the concept of an Operations with
you what tends to be different between
an Operations review and a typical agile
retrospective as the the level of
objectivity an Operations review
typically requires managers involved to
bring data data that's been collected
from the workflow system from the defect
tracking system and so on and report
that data report objective facts about
cycle times and throughput or velocity
and defect rates and perhaps efficiency
are waste equations which is the
combination of cycle time against
engineering touch time
to look at cumulative floor diagrams to
look at the number of blocking issues
that came to resolve issues facts
objective data agile retrospectives have
a tendency to be a lot more subjective
you know how did we feel about the last
sprint what did we like what didn't we
like what would we what what would we do
the same what would we do differently
they tend tends to be more subjective as
teams mature they might get more
objective but with Canberra and they try
and encourage teams to be objective
right from the beginning and again to
set a cadence for how often you have
these meetings so this is another
decoupling question agile methods couple
the retrospective to the release so if
you do two week iterations you do a
retrospective every two weeks well that
may be okay but what if you wanted to do
it once a month or once a week or some
other cadence so I encourage teams to do
these operation
reviews and to choose their own cadence
for that to decouple it from the release
of the planning cycle and to do it at
the organization level so not at the
individual project level get the whole
department together and report across
all the projects you're working on and
the reason why that's good is it allows
the cross-pollination of ideas from one
project to another and it encourages
organizational development and
organizational maturity and I believe
that as a factor and why we've seen
accelerated organizational maturity on
teams doing Kanban at the same time I
have seen Kanban teams do project level
or iteration level retrospectives often
when something doesn't quite go right
you know they've they've done a release
and there was some problem so they hold
our retrospective to analyze what went
wrong and how would we prevent it from
happening again in the future
we've also seen with both Kanban teams
and this is reported in the field rather
than sort of mandated by the you know
the gurus or the thought we does people
who have popped up on the internet and
said you know my team have stopped doing
retrospectives they do surely do
operations reviews but they don't do it
too recent retrospectives and when you
analyze why it turns out most of the
activity that normally happened in the
retrospective has moved into the daily
stand-up meeting and because they're
talking about process improvement every
day they don't need to do it at the end
of the iteration or when they do a
release it becomes a daily behavior
rather than every two weeks or every
once a month so really good Kanban teams
that develop a Kaizen culture are
continuously improving culture our
retrospect are doing the retrospective
every day so retrospectives get
de-emphasized in Kanban because they've
been replaced with a combination of the
stand-up meeting and the operations
review another interesting point is the
estimates is it true that in Kanban
systems it is completely wave to
estimate expenditures so so that's a
good question because the the earliest
examples we didn't ask me it turns out
the estimation is a choice if you if you
choose to make it one so often people
estimate something so they can then
promise some delivery date and that's
expected or anticipated the problem is
that probably not everything you do
really needs a hard delivery date and
then I'll hear people say well if you
don't make a commitment you know set
some delivery date make a commitment you
can't hold people accountable well my
feeling about that is you're setting an
artificial target and then you're
forcing people to meet it and that tends
to drive heroic behavior and there's
lots of evidence in the the process
improvement
and Quality Assurance world you know
teachings from from leaders like
headbutts damning that when you set
those kind of targets and and said an
expectation that it must be made people
respond with heroic behavior and when
the act heroically they stop improving
they just act heroically and again and
again and again and they stop learning
so advice from from Deming from Goldratt
from a number of other people some more
modern thinkers like John Seddon and the
United Kingdom who thinks about
improving service industries they talk
about removing targets so I feel that
estimates lead to two target dates that
lead to commitments that drive a
dysfunction that's undesirable on the
other hand sometimes you really do need
to hit a delivery date so you might have
a requirement say you're an investment
bank and the government has changed some
regulations and the renew regulation
begins on the 1st of October this year
if you don't change your software to
meet those regulations you're not
allowed to trade a particular derivative
or commodity well that's a very high
cost to your business if you don't meet
the requirement and don't deliver on
time you have to stop trading so clearly
it's of value to know that you're going
to deliver on time so for that
particular requirement it's worthwhile
making an estimate of how long will it
take if we think it will take six weeks
and we need it for the first of October
it would make sense to start it and very
early August it wouldn't make sense to
start it in me because early delivery
has really no value but if you're late
if you don't deliver until November you
lost a month of trading
so what Kanban says is use estimation
appropriately and
figure out when it's appropriate to you
to make an estimate and use that
intelligently so estimation becomes a
choice rather than estimating everything
you only estimate things which are
really important and really need an
estimate the idea of Kanban comes from
the auto mobile production where we have
to deal with constantly recurring
uniform procedures software projects
however have softmod the character of
product development therefore a very
creative and every time individual
process is Kanban at all suitable for
software projects or are the real
strength of Kanban more operation and
maintenance all right so that's a you
know it's a good question if anything I
hear that question more from
manufacturing guys so skeptical clearly
Kanban is useful for software projects
we've got too many people around the
world doing that now for it not to be
the case but it does beg a number of
interesting questions why why does it
work when clearly software development
has a lot more variability to it than
manufacturing and and that would lead to
to an analysis of how has Kanban adapted
to a different environment
they you know a software development
environment while I accept the fact that
software development is very creative I
don't think the process changes a huge
amount you know so if you look at games
industry for example you know if you ask
someone to to think up our part of the
software industry where there's
tremendous creativity and they're
pushing the limits really hard the games
industry would be one of those sectors
and yet it turns out that there's a lot
of Kanban adoption with games companies
because there's a lot of elements in
making games that follow particular
procedures the the production of games
not so much the programming but the
production of graphics
and data for the levels and side the
games and sound and perhaps animation
you nowadays to get really good
animation the you know they put stick
house on real people and they film them
and they watch how their arms and the
legs and their heads move and how the
bodies bend and they capture all that
data and they feed it into these you
know 3d graphics engines that then move
all the the polygons around to move
exactly the we real people move that's
games production and the there are
procedural elements and that certain
things have to be done fast before other
things you need to capture the data
before you can start you know animating
it and rendering it and so on and there
are different specializations there are
people that specialize in capturing data
and people that specialize in in
manipulating that data later on to me
you know give it the right look and feel
on the right gameplay and and so on so
Kanban has lent itself very well to that
because it helps them define that
process and then monitor you know how
the work is progressing through it at
the same time there is still much more
variability in software development than
there is in manufacturing processes you
know you could ask the question how long
does it take to do a user story and the
answer may be anything from half a day
to 10 DS well clearly you can't have
this concept that they have in
manufacturing of at act time if you look
at something like a production line for
Toyota Corollas the tag time may be 97
seconds and what that means is every 97
seconds are completed corolla rolls off
the end of the line how do they come up
with 97 seconds well that's actually
very easily answered the 97 seconds is
the three sigma apart
limit of the longest task on the
assembly line so there may be a task
that has a let's say it was some like
gluing the windscreen end to the car and
on average it takes eighty seconds and
the upper control limit is 97 and the
lower control limit is 73 so it's a
range of between 73 and 97 seconds and
that's the slowest task on the lane so
if they set the takt time to be 97
seconds the lane should never stop if
everything is running smoothly well you
couldn't have a concept of pact time for
software development you know what's the
what's the upper control limit on the
cycle time for developing and testing a
user story it's almost a nonsense
question on the other hand we've
developed a number of techniques in
software can burn that cope with
variability and different risk profiles
that really make the system very
flexible and capable of dealing with and
indeed sort of maximizing the value from
the variability concepts like the use of
classes of service
we're in manufacturing does typically
just two classes of service the standard
frost and frost out queuing and there's
expediting something's really argent and
in many Kanban systems they don't even
have that one so they only have frost
and frost out queuing and the reason
this works is that everything coming
through that Lane is essentially
homogeneous you know if you're
assembling a car and it needs a gearbox
well the gearbox that's coming next has
the same value is the one behind it and
the one behind that and the one behind
that so the cost of delay in one gearbox
being late is the same as the cost of
delay in the next one and the next one
and so on but with software development
the value is unique and different to
every single you
story so the cost of delay associated
with the user story you're working on
now will be different from the cost of
delay associated with the next one or
the one behind that or the one behind
that and you can use that information to
manage risk better and to produce a more
risk optimal outcome to deliver the most
value in the shortest period of time at
the lowest cost and the way you make
that happen is using classes of service
and dividing up different types of work
and assigning different classes of
service to those with different service
level agreements with different target
cycle times and delivery expectations
and by allocating the the total limit of
work see you had a limit of 20 things in
progress and total and you divide that
button by different classes of service
you allow the system to be flexible to
the idea that some things are big some
are smaller some can be done faster some
should be done slower they all have
different costs of delay so Kanban and
software started with the same
principles as manufacturing but they
evolved a different set of practices we
didn't try and copy the manufacturing
practices exactly in fact we didn't
train copy the manufacturing practices
at all we looked at the principles
applied those principles to software
development problems and evolved our own
set of practices so it's really not
derived from manufacturing other certain
industries or types of organizations to
which you would would advise against
kenmin well you know it's difficult to
define the negative we've seen
industries where Kanban is gaining
adoption so it has gained a lot of
adoption in IT maintenance you know
doing production bug fixes small
upgrades it seems a very natural fit for
that it's also gained adoption in IT
operations you know running tickets for
system mean
and system upgrades and that type of
thing we've seen can buy an adoption in
games companies I think primarily
because there's a lot of specialization
in games and the agile idea that you
have a generalist workforce doesn't work
very well for for games so the law the
specialization a lot of handoffs and
Kanban helps them optimize that problem
we've seen can buy an adopted an
investment banking I think because
investment bankers understand the risk
management concepts that that have
evolved in software Kanban we've also
seen Kanban being adopted in IT
departments of more traditional
industries automotive manufacturers like
Robert Bosch for example we are the know
about can buy and from the manufacturing
side of the business they know that it's
part of lean and they know that they've
used that technique to optimize the
performance of the manufacturing and it
makes them curious about how could we
use Kanban in the IT department just the
fact that other people are doing it and
talking about it is like wow you mean
this really works we never thought of
doing it there tell me more so we're
seeing adoption there but you know with
the B organizations where it it wouldn't
fit very well I'm sure that's going to
be true but I don't think we know enough
yet we haven't seen enough enough
adoption either globally or across
different industries and most of the
adoption that has taken place is not
reported publicly you know although we
have a good number of public key studies
and reports and magazine articles and
some books coming out we don't have
enough to really identify clusters of
the the negative Keys okay David
thank you very much for the interview
any last words on Kanban well thank you
for having me
I hope the answers have been useful and
have
clarified issues that the people might
have and you know my advice to to anyone
who is interested as try it Google on it
look up the limited web Society org
that's limited WIP
Society org which is the online home for
software Kanban and take a look at the
information there it links off to lots
of other external information and
articles and so much of this is
counter-intuitive
the only way to find out is to give it a
try
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SE
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team @ s e - radio net or if they're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
Creative Commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
Crowell and the pot site Music Network
for the music used in this show the song
is called Vegas on top